{"tossups": [{"question": "Many people fled this event on boats whose high passenger mortality rates inspired the nickname\u201ccoffin ships.\u201d During this event, the phrase \u201ctaking the soup\u201d was used to refer to families who accepted charity in exchange for converting to the Protestant faith. Robert Peel repealed the Corn Laws to provide relief for those impacted by, for ten points, what 1840s disaster caused by a<em> phytophthora</em> [FI-toe-THO-rah] blight of a certain crop?", "answer": "<b> Irish Potato Famine</b> (accept the<b> Great Famine</b>; accept the<b> Great Hunger</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This composer quoted \u201cCome, my dearest, why so sad this morning,\u201d in a piece written to benefit wounded Serbian soldiers in 1876. This composer celebrated Romanov imperialism with the polonaise that ends his<em> Symphony no. 3</em>, \u201cPolish.\u201d This composer of the<em> Marche Slave</em> used \u201cLa Marseillaise\u201d to represent Napoleon\u2019s invading army in an overture that, when played in the US, often accompanies fireworks. For ten points, name this Russian composer who included cannons in his<em> 1812 Overture</em>.", "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich<b> Tchaikovsky</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This body of water is home to the Isla del Sol and the Isla de la Luna, each of which contain ruins of a 15th-century civilization that flourished around its shores. Amantani Island is located on this lake and is currently home to thousands of Quechua-speaking peoples. This lake was viewed as sacred by the Incans, and is described as the highest navigable lake in the world. For ten points, name this lake that straddles the Bolivia-Peru border and is the largest lake in South America.", "answer": "Lake<b> Titicaca</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This province\u2019s Quiet Revolution secularized society in the 1960s. The Meech Lake and Charlottetown Accords tried to better integrate this province with its country. A 1995 referendum narrowly rejected independence for this province, where a 1970 crisis required the first peacetime use of the War Measures Act after the FLQ kidnapped Pierre Laporte in Montreal. For ten points, name this French-speaking Canadian province.", "answer": "<b> Quebec</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "At the end of his life, Marcus Aurelius told those around him \u201cweep not for me; think rather\u201d of those affected by one of these disasters; that disaster began during the reign of Antoninus Pius and is sometimes named after Galen. The port of Piraeus [pi-ray-us] is the estimated starting point of one of these disasters that began in 430 BC in Athens. Under Justinian, over 20 million people were killed in one of these that was caused by<em> Yersinia pestis</em>. Bubonic is a type of, for ten points, what type of widely-spreading disease?", "answer": "<b> plague</b>s (accept Antonine<b> Plague</b>; accept<b> Plague</b> of Galen; accept<b> Plague</b> of Athens; accept <b>Plague</b> of Justinian; accept bubonic<b> plague</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This event may have been called out of anger over Urban VIII\u2019s presentation as Simplicio in<em> Dialogue</em> <em>Concerning the Two Chief World Systems</em>. After this event, the central figure allegedly said \u201cand yet it moves,\u201d a refusal to accept this event\u2019s result. This event began with the accusation of teaching a \u201cfalse doctrine\u201d \u201cthat the Sun is the center of the world.\u201d The Roman Inquisition carried out, for ten points, what 17th century affair over an Italian astronomer\u2019s heliocentrism?", "answer": "the<b> trial</b> of<b> Galileo</b> Galilei (accept additional information; prompt on partial answers, such as \u201cheliocentrism trial\u201d or \u201cGalileo\u2019s house arrest\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this city\u2019s Kew Garden area, 38 neighbors allegedly watched Winston Moseley murder Kitty Genovese. In 1989, Matias Reyes committed a crime in this city but only confessed in 2002, well after full-page ads demanding the death penalty were made by Donald Trump. The Son of Sam murdered people during the summer of 1976 in, for ten points, what city whose police wrongly caught the Central Park Five?", "answer": "<b> New York</b> City (or<b> NYC</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Early members of this organization included Gustave Moynier, who caused a rift in its early years. The first Nobel Peace Prize was awarded jointly to pacifist Fr\u00b4ed\u00b4eric Passy and the founder of this organization, Henri Dunant, who was inspired after witnessing the carnage of the Battle of Solferino. For ten points, name this Geneva-based international organization that protects victims of war and whose member societies often provide medical services in disaster areas.", "answer": "International (Committee of the)<b> Red Cross</b> (accept International (Federation of)<b> Red Cross</b> and Red Crescent Societies; do not accept the American Red Cross or other nation-specific examples)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This American statesman names a foreign aid plan that rebuilt Western Europe after World War II.", "answer": "George<b> Marshall</b> (accept<b> Marshall</b> Plan)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This team was on the losing end of Don Larsen\u2019s World Series perfect game in 1956. In that year and seven others, this team lost to the Yankees in the World Series, though they won the 1955 World Series behind Duke Snider, Roy Campanella, rookie Sandy Koufax, and an infielder signed by Branch Rickey in 1947. For ten points, name this Major League Baseball team that moved to southern California in 1957 and broke the color barrier by signing Jackie Robinson to play in Brooklyn.", "answer": "Brooklyn<b> Dodgers</b> (accept Los Angeles<b> Dodgers</b> after \u201cseven others\u201d is read; accept <b>Brooklyn</b> until it is read; prompt on Los Angeles after \u201cseven others\u201d is read, but do not accept LA before then)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In this region, the Battle of Gergovia allowed some natives to keep their independence. In a 52 BC battle in this region, the attacking side built a wall around a besieged town, then built another wall around themselves. A work written about this region notes that it is \u201ca whole divided into three parts\u201dand describes the author\u2019s victory over Vercingetorix at Alesia. For ten points, name this region that was conquered by Julius Caesar and largely corresponds with modern-day France.", "answer": "<b> Gaul</b> (or<b> Gallia</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This country was led by Veselin Duranovic [dur-AH-no-VITCH] after the death of its longtime leader in 1980. A partisan resistance to the Nazi occupation of this country established a Communist government after the war, led by Josip Tito. The 1992 breakup of this country led to war crimes such as the Srebrenica [sreh-breh-neet-zah] Massacre and the Siege of Sarajevo. For ten points, name this federal Balkan country that included Serbia and Croatia.", "answer": "Socialist Federal Republic of<b> Yugoslavia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man employed logs to hamper paratroop landings, a tactic that became known as</b> <b>his namesake Asparagus when this man oversaw defenses at the Atlantic (+)</b> <b>Wall. While</b> <b>this man recovered from injuries sustained in a strafing raid, he was offered cyanide pills after he was implicated in the Valkyrie assassination plot against (*)</b> Hitler. This general fought an indecisive battle against Bernard Montgomery at El Alamein. For ten points, name this \u201cDesert Fox\u201dwho commanded Germany\u2019s Afrika Korps.", "answer": "Erwin<b> Rommel</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A character created by this author has thousands of children with his concubines who are born after seven month pregnancies. This author wrote about The General in</b><em><b> The </b><b>Autumn of the Patriarch</b></em><b> and described the final days of (+) Simon Bolivar in</b><em><b> The General </b><b>in His Labyrinth</b></em><b>. This author fictionalized a 1928 massacre of striking banana workers in Ci\u00b4enaga, a town in his native (*)</b> Colombia. For ten points, name this Nobel Prize-winning author of<em> One Hundred Years of Solitude</em>.", "answer": "Gabriel<b> Garcia Marquez</b> (prompt on Garcia or Marquez alone)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b>The outcome of this Supreme Court case helped trigger an economic panic that included the failure of the Ohio Life Insurance and Trust Company. John McLean and Benjamin</b> <b>Curtis (+)</b> <b>dissented from the majority opinion in this case, citing a lack of opposition</b> <b>to similar provisions in the Northwest Ordinance. The plaintiff of this case sued Irene (*) </b>Emerson, but was found not to have standing to sue for his freedom. For ten points, name this 1857 case in which Roger Taney [taw-nee] declared that African-Americans were not citizens.", "answer": "Dred<b> Scott</b> v.<b> Sandford</b> (accept either underlined portion; accept Dred Scott v<b> Sanford</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Joseph Ni\u00b4epce [nee-EPS] was one of the first practitioners of this medium, using it to create a view from his house. The 291 studio focused on this medium under the management</b> <b>of (+)</b> <b>Alfred Stieglitz. This medium was advanced by Louis Daguerre, who names an</b> <b>early form of this medium that reduced the necessary (*)</b> exposure time. For ten points, name this artistic process that Ansel Adams used to portray scenes from American national parks in the 20th century.", "answer": "<b> photo</b>graphy (accept word forms)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this industry that was centered in Chicago at the time of Upton Sinclair\u2019s<em> The Jungle</em>.", "answer": "<b> meatpacking</b> industry (accept word forms; accept descriptive answers involving<b> slaughtering</b>, <b>processing</b>, and/or<b> shipping meat</b>; prompt on partial answers, such as \u201cagriculture,\u201d \u201cmeat,\u201d \u201cshipping,\u201detc.; prompt on butchering and word forms)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>On a voyage to Panama, this man made a detour to attack the Canary Islands at the Battle of Las Palmas. During his Great Expedition, this privateer raided St. Augustine.</b> <b>With his cousin John Hawkins, this man organized (+)</b> <b>fireships and won against a fleet</b> <b>led by the Duke of Medina Sidonia. In 1587, this captain raided Cadiz, \u201csinging the beard of the King of Spain,\u201d seven years after a landmark voyage on the (*) </b> <em>Golden Hind</em>. For ten points, name this man, the first Englishman to circumnavigate the globe, who was employed by Elizabeth I and fought the Spanish Armada.", "answer": "Sir Francis<b> Drake</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This king is often speculated to be Amraphel, the Biblical king of Shinar. Shortly before his death, this king defeated Ishme-Dagan I and forced Assyria to pay tribute to him. This king\u2019s most famous creation was a set of 282 (+) rules discovered in Susa in 1901. This ruler is depicted with Shamash at the top of an Akkadian-language monument that commands,\u201cIf a man destroy the (*)</b> eye of another man, they shall destroy his eye.\u201d For ten points, name this Babylonian ruler who wrote an early law code.", "answer": "<b> Hammurabi</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>This cause was the subject of many speeches at the Hambach Festival. The</b> <b>Carlsbad Decrees put an end to fraternities known as burschenschaft that pushed for</b> <b>this cause. A customs union called the (+)</b> <b>Zollverein was an important step during</b> <b>this process. The liberal ideas of this movement were at odds with the Concert of</b> <b>Europe, orchestrated by Klaus von (*) </b> Metternich. The revolutions of 1848 called for, for ten points, what cause, advocated for by nationalists at the Frankfurt Parliament, that brought together Bavaria, Prussia, and other states into one country? ANSWER:<b> German unification</b> (accept equivalents for unification, do not accept or prompt on reunification)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}